(light playful music)
Welcome to the first section
in this complete Node.js bootcamp.
And in this section,
we will take our very first steps with Node.js
and its core modules by building a small and fun project.
So my goal with the section
is to get you writing Nodes.js code as fast as possible,
but without worrying too much about how everything works
behind the scenes,
because that will follow in later sections.
So we will start using a lot of new concepts
all at the same time here,
and so don't worry, if you don't understand
all the technical details right away.
That's just completely normal, all right?
Anyway, let's now get started on this journey.
(light playful music)