Now before diving into some NodeJS code,
let's do a high level overview
of what NodeJS actually is,
what we use it for and why we use Node
instead of other technologies.
So, the official definition is that
NodeJS is a JavaScript Runtime
built on Google's open-source V8 JavaScript engine.
Now, what does that actually mean?
Well, let's start by trying to understand
what the JavaScript Runtime
and the V8 engine actually are.
So, you have probably already used JavaScript before
and it was probably always just inside a browser, right?
Because any browser natively understands
HTML, CSS, and JavaScript and no matter
if you write vanilla JavaScript or some
JavaScript framework like React or Angular code,
that's all just JavaScript
that gets executed right in the browser.
So, in this case, the browser
is then the JavaScript Runtime.
But, what if we could take JavaScript
out of the browser and simply execute
or JavaScript code somewhere else without
all the restrictions that we have in the browser?
Well, it turns out that we actually can.
And the solution for this, as you can guess,
is called NodeJS and so Node JS
is just another JavaScript Runtime.
It's just like a container, like an environment,
in which a program written in JavaScript
can be executed, but outside of any browser whatsoever.
All right, it's actually a bit more complex
than this, of course, but for now, this is enough.
Now, who actually does execute
the code if not the browser?
And that's where the V8 engine
developed by Google comes into play.
Because that is exactly where JavaScript code
will be parsed and run in NodeJS, okay?
So, I hope that now the definition of NodeJS
being a JavaScript Runtime on the V8 JavaScript engine
makes a lot more sense and again,
this is just a very high level overview
of what Node is and how it works.
We are gonna go into a lot of detail
about how Node really works behind the scenes
right in the next section, but at this point,
I just want you to get a quick overview
so that you can start learning the fundamentals
of NodeJS in practice throughout this section.
Anyway, now that we have JavaScript
outside of the browser in a kind of
stand alone environment which just NodeJS,
we can do so many more things with JavaScript
that were completely impossible before
like accessing the file system,
or better networking capabilities
are not possible with NodeJS
and all these factors together give us
the perfect conditions for using NodeJS as a web server
meaning that now we can finally use JavaScript
on the server side of web development
in order to build fast, highly scalable
network applications for powering the back-end
all for websites or web applications.
And this is absolutely fantastic
and game-changing for web development.
So, let's now take a look at some use cases for Node
and why it's such a great fit for back-end development.
And the first thing that we need to talk about
is the fact that Node applications
are so fast and so scalable because NodeJS
is single threaded based on
an event driven, non-blocking I/O model
which makes NodeJS very lightweight and efficient.
Now, that, of course, sounds super complicated,
I know, but once more we're gonna talk about
exactly what all of this means
a little late in the course.
But, for now, just keep in mind
that Node is perfect for building super fast,
and scalable data-intensive web applications.
And that makes NodeJS a perfect fit for building
all different kinds of applications like
building an API with a database behind it
and preferably a non-relational NoSQL database like MongoDB
and this is actually exactly what we're gonna do later
in this course as we dive deeper and deeper into NodeJS.
But, there is, of course, all sorts of other apps
that we can build like data streaming applications
such as YouTube or Netflix, real-time chat apps,
or even server-side web applications
where the entire content is simply generated
right on the server, so as you see,
the possibilities really are endless.
But, there is actually, also, a type of apps
that we should not build with Node.
And this is when our app needs
some super heavy server-side processing
like having image manipulations, video conversion,
file compression or anything like that, all right.
And you will learn why that is once we dive deeper
into how Node actually works.
So, in this case, we're better off
using something like Ruby on Rails, PHP, or Python.
Because NodeJS just wasn't developed
for these use cases and although there are solutions
for dealing with them, we should always use
the right tool for the task at hand.
Okay, so these are the types of applications
that we can and cannot build using NodeJS.
And if you choose to use Node,
well, then you are in good company because
many top companies like Netflix, Uber, PayPal,
Ebay and many many more have already started using
NodeJS which really proves that the technology
is stable enough at this point to be used in production.
Now, of course there are more reasons for using Node,
and the biggest one is probably that using
the same language across your entire stack
both on the front-end and the back-end
is a lot easier for you or for your team.
First, you don't have to learn
a new programming language for building
your back-end and, also, you don't have to
keep switching back and forth between language
which will make the entire building process
faster and more efficient.
Believe me, it's really really amazing
to be able to use JavaScript to build
your entire application from start to finish.
It's absolutely fantastic really.
And another great reason for using Node
is that there is a huge library of open-source packages
or modules, as we can also call them,
available for everyone for free.
It's called NPM and you've probably heard of it
or even used it already.
And, of course, we're also gonna start
using packages right in the section.
And, finally, it's also good to know
that there is a huge active community
of Node developers out there that are constantly
improving NodeJS and helping beginners like you.
And, so you can really rely on the technology
for all your projects in the years to come.
Okay, so that was a very brief intro
and overview of NodeJS and some of it's use cases.
So, for the rest of this section,
we will now use Node to create
a very simple web server and build
an extremely simple API, so that
you can get familiar with
the basic principles of Node development.